hello everyone i'm jacob calif and i'm
the nerd in the street and today we're
taking a look at lotte doc alright
everyone so for a long time the doc in
mac OS has been a big defining factor of
the mac OS desktop if you've ever seen a
screenshot of a mac you've seen that doc
probably at the bottom of the screen
where it is by default and for many
years there have been programs that have
attempted to add the doc to Windows or
Linux computers because people who don't
have max still might like the idea of
having a doc where all of their icons go
it's actually not the most efficient use
of space but it is pretty and easy to
understand and so quite a while ago I'm
talking probably around 2010 I tried out
many different free open source Doc's on
Linux there were quite a few options
back in the day most of them are no
longer being actively developed today
because most of them were pretty
gimmicky the point was just to copy the
max dock onto your Linux computer
however recently within the past couple
of years there has been a new dock in
development and it's gotten quite
popular that dock is called lot a dock
and what makes it very interesting is
that unlike a lot of these standalone
dock gimmicks these little apps that
have existed just to add the dock that
have existed in the past
lot a dock it's built on the KDE plasma
panel system KDE is extremely
configurable if you're using a plasma
desktop you can already add new panels
resize panels move things around on your
panels and so what lot a doc does is it
registers itself as a plasma panel that
means it integrates extremely nicely
into your KDE desktop you can put KDE
widgets into the dock and it also
provides an app launching functionality
similar to a Mac OS dock so I was
actually using lot a dock for a little
while on my machine I'm no longer using
it on a regular basis just because like
I said it's not actually a very
efficient use of space most of the time
when I need to launch an application I
hit the meta key to open up the
kickoff menu the Start menu and plasma
and I start typing for the application I
want which searches and then I just
press Enter when the search result comes
up and so taking up space with a big row
of icons and then having to move my
mouse on to those icons when I want to
open up an application it was cool to
have it's not exactly my cup of tea for
actually having my desktop set up that
way but obviously Mac OS is very popular
and a lot of people might want a dock
out there so just in case you're looking
to spice up your desktop maybe you're
using KDE and the default windows like
layout is just getting a little boring I
thought it might be fun to take a look
at latte doc so without further ado
we're gonna go ahead and cut to the
desktop alright guys and here we are on
my desktop I have adjusted my screen
resolution to actually be 1920 by 1080
for this video because with a doc I'm
not gonna be able to crop the video very
easily so depending on your Linux
distribution you might use a different
package manager to install latte doc but
I did take a look and it looks like the
package is called latte - doc on every
major distribution so these are the
commands you would use depending on what
distro you are on and once you have
latte doc installed you may need to
start it you can add it to your KDE
autostart settings if you are using KDE
plasma or there a variety of different
ways to auto launch applications
depending on the desktop environment
you're using but if I open up latte doc
here you can see it opens up where I had
it configured at the top of my screen
and this is what I had mine configured
to look like when I was using it this is
actually not really the default look at
all but as you can see latte doc is a
flat design that's one thing that I do
wish was different about it it's this 2d
box design which looks very similar
actually to the current Mac OS desktop
this is a screenshot of the latest
version of Mac OS and it's really
interesting because Apple went back to
this 2d design as well so latte doc
actually matches what you get on a
current Mac but I always think it's
funny the current Mac OS doc being 2d it
looks extremely similar to the Mac OS
Tiger doc which this was around the
windows XP era in terms of years and it
was also a 2d doc as you can see it
looks about the same as what they have
today now around the time that Windows
Vista came out Apple came out with Mac
Leopard and it had this 3d dock and this
was what a lot of the apps that I
mentioned earlier tried to replicate was
this 3d reflective shelf I just think
that this looks a lot cooler than the
previous tiger dock and I couldn't
believe it when Apple went back in time
to the older flat design so if there was
a skin or a theme for a lot a dock that
would add this 3d sort of reflective
dock like Mac OS Leopard head then I
might start using it again on a
day-to-day basis just because it looks
so cool but yeah I did just want to draw
the comparison to Mac OS since obviously
that's what a lot of people know about
docks from now since I've already
configured this it's not really a fair
example right off the bat of what lot a
dot can do and what it's like to
actually use it so I am going to remove
my current lot a dot config and I am
going to kill lot a dock here and after
doing that I am going to open it up
again and this is what it looks like by
default if you've never used it before
it's going to show up at the bottom of
your screen and it's going to show you
the running applications on your system
incidentally I have nine virtual
desktops and I've cut quite a few other
applications running right now so that's
why you're seeing this so as you can see
by default lot a dock is going to place
itself on the bottom of your screen
which is going to sort of conflict with
the default plasma panel I am going to
try and move this plasma panel let me
unlock my widgets panel options
configure panel screen edge let's drag
the default panel to the top of our
screen because this looks similar ish to
Mac OS obviously Mac OS doesn't have a
Start menu at the top left of the screen
but now we can have the dock at the
bottom of our screen behaving normally
so by default there is a sort of shelf
design you can see it is 2d it's not
reflective or anything but we've just
got indicators for all of our running
applications and quite a large zoom
factor by default as well so we can
right click on this dock and we can go
to dock settings which is going to let
us configure our dock with the lot a
dock settings manager we can select
which screen it's showing up on I've got
two displays plugged in right now and
we're showing on the primary display you
can display the dock on any edge of the
screen just like
Mac OS I'm not even sure Mac OS lets you
display the doc on the top of the screen
but you can see we can display on the
left side here which might remind you a
little bit of the Ubuntu unity desktop
environment and a lot of people have
been using Lotte doc to sort of
replicate that setup as well but
switching back to the bottom of the
screen here since that is the iconic
positioning we can set our alignment if
you want your dog to show up in one of
the corners here of course we can decide
how we want the doc to behave in terms
of hiding and showing itself if you want
your doc to always hide itself whether
there's a window there or not you can do
that so now the doc doesn't show up
unless we actually move our mouse to the
bottom of the screen we can set the doc
to always be visible or we can do what I
was doing which is dodging active
windows and so if I open up K right here
and I drag it on to this side of the
screen
you can see right now the doc is on the
screen and as soon as I drag this window
down here the doc is going to move out
of the way because this is an active
window now if I click off of this window
it's no longer active so the doc comes
back but if I move my focus back to this
window the doc goes away again so you
can have that happen you can have it
only dodge maximized windows you can
have it dodge all windows even if
they're not active so it really does
just depend on how you want this to
behave and you can configure it
accordingly it's great that the
configurability is there because this is
highly subjective now I find that the
default delay for hiding and showing is
a little bit too long I like it to hide
itself a little bit quicker and to show
itself pretty much immediately when I
move the window as you can see onto the
dock and then away from the dock it
comes up much quicker after adjusting
that once again great configurability we
can also take a look at our appearance
tab here this is where we can set the
initial size of the icons so I usually
like to make my dock a little bit
smaller because it makes me feel like my
screen is bigger but for this video we
probably want to set the icons a little
bit bigger so you guys can see them
better you can select your zoom
percentage and once again I find the
default zoom percentage a little bit too
much it looks too cartoony this is a bit
more even maybe a little lower yeah I
find that that subtle zooming is much
better much more elegant in my
in the length here doesn't really affect
anything with the default settings
although you can set a sort of override
for the maximum length of the dock say
to 50 percent of your screen by default
the dock is only going to take up as
much space as it needs and down here you
can turn on or off that background and
you can increase the size of the
background for instance the way that I
did to make it look a little bit more
like Mac OS with the full box behind the
dock or you can make it smaller to
pretend like there's a shelf down there
even though really it's just a box you
can also make it slightly transparent
which i think is really nice we'll make
it about 50% there and now if we close
our settings you can see what it looks
like and if we put a window back there
and then we click off of it
well that transparency does not exactly
seem to be working which is interesting
to see moving on from that little quark
though we've got one last tab in our
simple settings here and this has to do
with tasks tasks are how plasma is going
to separate out what is displayed in
this particular panel and what is not
for instance like I said I've got nine
virtual desktops running so most of
these applications are on those other
desktops I've got a blender render
running you know what I didn't want to
stop that when I came and made this
video so we can filter our dock to just
the current virtual desktop with a
checkbox right here and you can see most
of that stuff falls out and now we've
just got the things that I'm using to
record here we can also show only tasks
from our current screen so I'm on a
multi-monitor setup right now and now
you're not seeing the recording
applications anymore because they're all
on the other screen of course if I drag
one of these things onto the screen then
it will show up in the dock and if I
drag it back off the screen then it goes
away so I'm gonna leave those options
checked to make the rest of this video a
little bit easier to understand and
right now we have a pretty functional
dock we've got a couple of shortcuts in
here I can open up a new Firefox window
it opened on the wrong screen there but
it did open let's try a dolphin here
once again opened on the incorrect
screen but you can see when we do have
an application open we've got the little
dots that is signifying that the
application is running in the background
and then whatever is currently selected
is going to have that full line
underneath it
I think the app running indicators look
very nice nothing really to be desired
there and
my opinion now there are some advanced
options for latte dock you can actually
have more than one dock on your screen
at the same time which i think is just
getting to be a little bit too much
let's close this OOP well I just closed
an application there but let's try and
remove this side dock because I only
want the bottom one right now but since
these are like plasma panels like I said
before you can add multiple of them and
configure them differently we can also
turn on our Advanced Settings here and
that is going to give us some extra
options for instance right now the dock
is running in dock mode but we can
actually change it to panel mode in
which case it's going to be a full bar
across the screen just like a normal
plasma panel so it's interesting that
you can do that as well with the
Advanced Options turned on we've got
some additional settings in each of our
sections up here right now you can see
we've got the tooltips of the names the
windows showing up when we hover over
these items we can turn that off if we
want you can see this option is turned
on by default to activate items through
the mouse wheel so I can actually use my
mouse wheel to scroll over an icon
I can't scroll through the items like I
can with my top plasma dock but if you
hover over an item and you scroll at all
then it's going to select that option if
we come over to appearance here you can
see we've got some extra options in the
Advanced section as well let's increase
the size of our background here again to
better see some of these options we can
choose to draw an outline around our
dock which sort of frames it we can turn
off the blur in the back of the dock and
the shadow we can change our theme here
as you can see which is interesting this
lighter color looks even more like the
current version of Mac OS you can see it
is sort of glitching our analog clock
there and so we'll turn it back to
plasma and as you can see there are some
small glitches here this application is
not perfectly written there are a lot of
just little visual glitches and that's
what a lot of people give k2e a hard
time for in general and lot a dock I
find KDE itself doesn't really have a
lot of those anymore but lot a dock is
definitely a little bit more rough
around the edges since it is an add-on
to KDE and that's again one of the
reasons why I'm not using it but if you
are wanting this sort of interface I
think
that it's certainly stuff you can work
through so the Advanced Options also
open up this entirely new section of our
settings called effects by default when
we do open up an application you can see
our icon bounces for a second there
which is cool but you can turn that off
if you want we can change our indicator
theme as well from the default to the
plasma indicator which is more similar
to the the lines that we have underneath
our taskbar items you can see those
lines on top of the icons now we can
still put them at the bottom of the dock
which looks a bit better I'm actually
gonna turn that back because I don't
think that looks as good you can't put
those little lights on top of the icons
if you want to do that for some reason
if we have more than one window of an
application open at the same time then
it is going to have more than one dot
and we can configure the way that those
work as you can see now the the several
dots still appear even when one of those
is active so really just all kinds of
configurability here you could play with
this for quite a while with all these
different settings in true KDE nature
now by default these are all actually
the same widget these three icons right
here and then we do have an analog clock
widget as you can see it's displaying
the time and then I can also click on it
to get a calendar just like our digital
clock and the top right of the screen
but these three widgets here or these
three icons are all part of a single
launcher widget if the latte tasks
applet is what it's called and we can
remove it with this button and so now
that's gone and you might be wondering
why we would want to do that well I
actually got to a point on my system
where I didn't want to use latte doc to
switch between applications I just
wanted to use it as a launcher so I
didn't care about having the indicators
underneath the icons anymore because I
was going to continue using the taskbar
to switch between apps when I've got a
lot of different windows open I just
find it's more efficient to for instance
dolphin here I can switch between the
two different windows really easily with
a drop-down list or a pop-up list I can
see thumbnails of each one of the
windows with the default plasma panel
and so I just find it's not as efficient
to click on a doc and then you can see I
have this weird fullscreen thing that
comes up where I can select the window
it's fine when there's two windows but
Firefox for instance I've got I've got
way too many windows open and Firefox
for that to work so I've got my
that I usually use with all my different
virtual desktops and my my taskbar but I
didn't want to use Lotte Docs since it
looked cool just as a launcher and so
what I did was I went into the doc
settings I went to the bottom of the
tasks section and I removed the tasks
applet now we can come down here to our
dock and like I said this is a plasma
panel we can add all the same widgets to
this panel as we can for all of our
other panels so if we come down here and
we click add widgets I can add a quick
lunch widget and I'm gonna drag that
into my dock here and now I can right
click on this and add a launcher and I
can select for instance Firefox so once
again this widget is no longer a tasks
widget it's not going to show me if an
item is open or not but it will continue
to launch new instances of Firefox when
I click on it now there are a couple
problems with using this quick launch
widget for one thing you can probably
tell that the Firefox icon is stuck a
little lighter than it's supposed to be
right now that's a visual glitch in
latte doc if we actually turn down the
size of our icons a little bit so now
the Firefox icon is at least fitting a
little better in our dock the lightness
bug is still there so once again that's
why I stopped using it were those kinds
of visual glitches but obviously I'm
well outside the normal use case for
this right now
now if I come to this quick launch and I
add some more launchers here let's say I
want Kay right as a launcher and I also
want musescore as a launcher you can see
that that launcher is now tiny and it's
showing up all is one icon in our dock
if I make the dock a little bit smaller
or full make the icons a little bit
smaller oh I guess if I make them bigger
that will at least cause them all to
display at a normal I concise however
now they're not zooming because it's all
one big item that has always just zoomed
in you can see my analog clock still
zooms but this quick launch does not
zoom so what I ended up doing was I
dragged a bunch of different quick
launch widgets down here which is going
to use more RAM actually on your system
but now I can add a single launcher to
each quick launch widget I can do
Firefox on that one I can do Kay right
on this one and I can do musescore in
this quick launch widget so this is
using more RAM but it does look nicer
and now I can come back
my dock settings and I can make the
icons a little bit smaller so that those
show up a little nicer there and now
they zoom normally or fairly normally as
well so yeah this is the way that my
dock was configured when I first opened
it up and I had a bunch of different
icons at the top of the screen at the
beginning of this video this was how it
was using it and I actually removed the
clock because I don't find that
particularly helpful a tiny little
analog clock that's almost too small for
me to see but yeah if you're wanting to
shake up your your desktop a little bit
if you find yourself getting bored with
the default desktop and you want to play
around with a different sort of style or
if you're just looking for a nicer
looking quick launch option I know you
can add quick launch icons to your
default plasma taskbar but it might not
look very nice so this is a much nicer
looking at you know a very pretty quick
launch bar if you're wanting to add one
of those this program is absolutely here
and you're absolutely welcome to use it
this is an official KDE app at this
point it is sort of an add-on it's not
part of plasma but it is on the KDE
infrastructure so you can find a git
mirror on KDE s github page and you can
also find lot a dock on the KDE Store
interestingly enough as a plasma 5
add-on so I hope that that's at least a
little bit entertaining I hope somebody
out there sees that and decides to play
around with it if this video was helpful
or entertaining to you I would ask that
you go to nerd club not schoo the link
is down in the description and consider
becoming a nerd club member for just
three dollars a month I really enjoy
showing off these little Linux apps and
I'd love to have more time and resources
to make more of these videos but for
right now that's everything I had to
talk about so i'm jacob cough and i'm
the nerd of the street and i'll see you
guys in the next one bye
[Music]